Okay, we are now going to call the order of the regular city council meeting for today's date.
Item two is public input and on schedule personal approaches.
Anyone the audience wishes to address the council on any of the agenda items.
There are being none.
Item three is consent agenda staff is recommending items four through seven for the consent agenda.
Item seven being that same master services are given that we just discussed.
So for this meeting, they're just asking it to be on the consent agenda.
Any questions or any of those items, if not, we have a motion to approve the consent agenda.
A motion to approve.
Second please.
Second, roll call.
Johnson.
Four, sir?
Five.
Question.
Shots.
I have a number.
Item number.
And this presentation of Street Study and Plan Recommendation.
Sean is that on a hay?
On a hay.
Welcome Sean.
Thank you.
Well, the last time I saw you, I was driving Street.
So I've got done with that.
And from that, we put together this report that's sitting front of you.
And we're not going to go through a page by page.
Thank you.
Appreciate that.
Yeah, I don't think anybody wants to be here all night.
So with that, what we found, City's got 112 miles of street.
There's another six miles of departmental streets is what I'm going to call them at your wastewater
plant.
Water station, airport, fairgrounds, stuff like that.
They're not technically public, but you still maintain them.
Then there's 24 acres parking lot out there, too.
So this is kind of an idea of where all we was at.
So this is a Street Classification chart.
It's a little rough to see.
You're a big green and red lines.
Those are your major street.
Sean, I think Neil was trying to ask you.
This is a clean valley, too.
Was this a clean valley?
Yes.
We did look at those, too.
Those are included in that 112 miles.
Okay.
So green and red, those are your major streets.
Purple is what's classified as secondary by your guys' data.
They're actually your secondary snow routes.
Blue on there is your departmental streets and yellow is residential locals and then the
little black lines in there are your alleys.
And then these are your parking lots that you guys maintain out of your 24 acres.
Most of those are your downtown parking lots and then you've got three acres sitting
right here at the Civic Center.
So kind of a breakdown of what we found.
We'll start with the alleys.
Out of your 16 miles of alleys that you have.
You've got 86% of them that are unimproved, so they're either gravel or dirt, so if we take them out of the list and not look at them as really a pavement failure
Half of the city streets are in need of some sort of maintenance or repair or total replacement
Another 20% of those are in need of maintenance
So they don't continue to deteriorate
And 50% of the city's parking lots are in need of the maintenance or repair
Part mental streets actually aren't in that bad shape, most of them are concrete
So you've actually only got like 9% of them that need something done to them
And one of them is out there at the fairground where you've got that little blowout on the road
And then the other ones at OPC
Payments getting a little rough out there, but I wouldn't put it very high in the priority way, so
So this is a breakdown map of the ratings of the streets
And anything red or yellow is a pavement failure or a base failure
Hmm?
I don't know, I don't know
Where's the good news?
So we'll get to that
I don't think there are a few things to say to keep respect to them
Okay, so they don't don't jump out the window
So anything red or yellow, we're going to recommend replacement
Just because off of the geotech reports that I've read that you've had done in the past
There's not much to the streets here
Pretty thin asphalt
There are two to six inches of asphalt over a river sand base
To no base at all
Some places you may not run into that, you may actually have a decent street that's got a little base rock under it
We may be able to do something a little simpler there
But until we get in, start digging them up, we're not really going to know
Those are those findings, this two to six inches of asphalt over
I think you said a river sand base, is that uncommon for small towns like ours?
No, not really
That's pretty normal
Especially where you're at because the river sand would have been something cheap and readily available
I'm actually more surprised, it's not chat
So
But looking at the rating system is a zero to five
So zero is no pavement, that was just an easy way for me to track it
So any of your gravel streets that you've got out there, I gave them a zero
One and two are minimal cracking, they don't need anything done with most of your new micro surface streets
You've even got some older roads that are still a one and two class that aren't doing too bad
Three is something that should probably get a little maintenance soon
So if they don't continue to fail, and then four is a pavement failure of some kind
So you're alligator cracking
and your light-ready stuff like that, those are falling that class, and then five is a base failure.
So, um, I'm trying to think of where you would see that at.
Some of the places where right along the gutter, there's a really deep ret,
and you can actually see soil shoving up through the pavement. That's a base failure.
So, there's several of them out there, and most of that is due to,
they're not being any base under them, or four drainage.
So, with that, we're trying to, we use some local costs that we've used in Missouri on some things,
and a little bit down here, and came up with a recommended budget.
And what we did is, most of your maintenance activities,
they've got about a seven-year life cycle to them.
So, we broke that down in that method, and we ran it out 35 years.
That kind of helps us take care of all of the streets,
and then you start just a pure maintenance cycle.
So, what we did is in the first seven years, we go in,
and we start looking at all your major streets, and start doing some rebuilds on those,
and get them back up in a good shape.
And then after that cycle, we went and took your secondary roads,
and we spread them over a little bit longer period just because there's a lot more of them out there.
And then we start working your immediate maintenance stuff in there,
starting at year one, and it runs out for the first two cycles.
And I couldn't get all of this in there.
This is actually in the Pindex C of that record.
It's got a little more breakdown to it.
So, but from that, you really, I mean, one and a half million dollars
will cover all maintenance.
So, that's the good news, actually.
But we've got to get to that point first.
We've got a lot of rebuild stuff we've got to do, and some stuff that can't just have maintenance on it
to get back in shape.
And in order to do that, we've got to come up with an additional $5 million a year
for 35 years to cover that.
Or a $6 million a year budget will cover maintenance rebuilds,
basically the way we've got to grow out, and by the end of 30 unit.
By the end of the 35 years, you're at $168 million dollars.
So, no, we need to wait for their hearts to start.
Yes.
So, get your back and continue.
So, are you saying now that at the end of that 35 years that,
hypothetically, then, from there on a million and a half a year would keep all the rows,
we'll keep them in.
maintained. But we've got to get to that point first. Now this budget that includes
everything, hours. If they're gravel we had it figured in there to go in and put
some kind of hard surfacing. I'd actually price to do a chip seal on those like
a lot of county roads are. It's a cheap effective means. It works well. That also
includes your rehabs on all your city parking lots, all your departmental
pavement. If it needed anything that's in there. So this is everything. All
pavement maintained by the city is in that 35-year plan. So it is a big plan.
So it's not about your inflation factor. What are you assuming? That's just a
that's it's a 1.4% inflation. That's just to give us a little cushion in there.
That way whenever you look out 10-15 years gives you a little better idea.
annually what those costs will go up. The concern that we have right now with a
lot of the estimates that we're doing is asphalt is at an all-time low right
now. And as soon as the oil market goes back to the other direction, those asphalt
prices are going to skyrocket. So they are very heavily dependent on oil price.
I don't see any rebuild money in years 29 through 35. By the time we get to that point we
have actually re-builds are actually completed by year 21. We have pretty much
rebuilt everything. And then from during the third cycle, the 2018 through 28, we've
actually assumed that you will need to go back in and rebuild a certain portion of the
streets that don't need any maintenance today. And it's just a flaw to be honest with
you. It's an assumption that those streets that are 1s and 2s now may need something in
the future, but we only considered 20 or 30% of those streets would need something at that
time. And then by the time you're through that fourth cycle, it's a pure maintenance by then.
And that maintenance actually works out years 29 through 34 that steps down actually that increases
because that's starting to add in that last section of roads that you've just finished rebuilding
on your major stuff. So that year 35 of maintenance is a typical average of what you would be spending
per year on maintenance only. So about 1.4. So I sat down and I met with Dean in the Leetion
Highler last week and we went over there and I know you guys don't have that budget. But I do know
that you have right now planned 2.5 million dollars for next year and probably 1.1.5 million dollars
after that. So I did a budget for those.
And they look a little more realistic.
Is that what I'm saying?
Does that end here too?
It is in there.
It's in the, it's in a Pindex C, I believe.
It's by itself and in other Pindex Cs.
This doesn't cover everything.
This covers what can we fix now with the proposed budget we've got.
So what we're going to recommend that you would probably do is start on your majors.
D Street, main, the central, rock nail, send the dose.
And I'm going to jump forward once.
This is actually the map of who wants it.
We would recommend their grades for three and four right now.
So some of the little maintenance, some of the needs of rework to them.
Your lines that are in red would be the primary.
So they would be your first round.
And once we get through those that repair and maintenance budget kind of gains a little capital to it.
And then we can start on those streets that are marked in green.
Well, they should, can you point out the civics in there on there so I can get a worry at it.
Okay.
Here is third, fourth, B Street.
I don't know what it's at.
The C. Park Street right here.
Okay.
There you go.
Yeah, it's it's turned on its side.
So sorry.
We've got my arrow on that one.
So we're north in is north is to the north is to the left.
Okay.
So your primary roads that we've got marked is of course your truck route.
I mean that's a heavily traffic road.
Main streets always kind of on a priority list.
Just to finish up that section.
You guys have done a good job in the downtown.
Getting that fixed up.
It looks great down there.
So we could go ahead and finish up that last few blocks and get to railroad tracks and then all of your section looks the same.
And that includes in front of the Coleman with the drainage and also the stop sign in the middle of the intersection.
Yes.
And then.
Uh.
E-North East is actually a street that is most of us designed right now.
Um, by Anderson, but.
We with your budget, you've got planned.
You could actually work that in and work the rest of it out.
So go ahead and take care of the rest of it until you get to the street.
And you get connected with the piece that you've had rebuilt recently.
Did you say B nor these to E.
D-E.
E-North East is the one marked in.
red and then it ties in to D on the north end and runs out to the veterans.
Doesn't front of the nursing home.
Yeah.
And that maps in there with that budget.
And the business is good, then.
That's enough.
Up in to D.
Up in to D is the budget that we're talking about right now.
What was your study done basically on a visual of the street or was it based on traffic counts?
The pavement condition assessment was just visual.
And actually an appendix D is the guide that we used.
We built this guide actually for the city of Joplin after the tornado.
We worked with trans systems and we drove through the entire damage path and rated their streets.
And it has a one to five rating systems.
So we did the exact same thing here and use the same ratings.
And it's just a visual inspection only.
But it covers your streets and your coping gutters and your sidewalks.
No, no, no, course.
No, no, no, no, no.
Extend of what repairs or no, we don't know what's underneath it.
Other than the geotech reports that I've gotten that you guys have had done in the past.
Most of them's my Anderson.
That's where I got kind of the what the typical pavement's made out of around here is reading through those.
You made a comment in regards to, you know, like mainstream just because it's heavily traffic area.
You know, one of the things that I get feedback with some of the people in my ward and I'm sure a lot of people in the other ward is
is that you say it's visual.
But are we a lot of people can understand why do we fix a certain road that doesn't get much traffic?
You know, although it's visually bad if you don't have one or two people going down it.
Why would you want to fix that one over one that you got multiple people that, you know, doesn't look as bad.
But it's got a lot of traffic.
So can you cover that?
So this budget here shouldn't have any of those that only have one or two cars a day.
These are your major collectors and your urban arterioles.
These are heavy streams.
Right.
Now the other plant, the recommended budget that has every street.
If there's one house on it and it needs something, it's in the plan just because it needs all the other streets that look just like it are in there.
Now when you actually sit down and you start priorities in that budget, those need to be worked around because I do agree with you.
Some of those streets that only have one or two cars on a day, maybe they don't need to be asphalt.
Maybe you just go back and with the...
a chip and seal on them, or you let them go back to gravel.
I know a lot of people don't like that, but there's nothing wrong with it, and in a
stormwater sense, it's actually not a bad idea, because it's not hard surface.
Do we know the condition of the gas lines, zirlines, water lines, we will have that at
the end of this month.
I am starting on that one tomorrow.
It's a two-fold process that we have, if you remember, the streets were first and then
utilities a month after this, so we're getting a bad idea.
Yeah, we're going to do the same, it's basically going to be the same thing as this.
It'll be, I don't know what's down in the ground, I've talked to Chris a little bit, I kind
of have an idea of some of their video stuff, what they've got, and typical line stuff, and
we're going to make a budget recommendation on that, it'll be a blanket coverage, though, for
water and sewer, kind of, this is what we think you need to do on all of them.
Most of your sewer lines are a clay, so we have a recommendation for that, but that will be
next month.
And some of these streets will need to be held off until we figure out what we want to do with
utilities.
I agree with that.
One central is the water line that's underneath it, needs replaced as well, and there's
no sense in being rebuild in the street, and then cut and adapt to replace the water line
underneath it afterwards.
So that will not leave anybody happy when you get done, you're right.
So, hopefully we can work out some of these to where we can get a utility budget, and a street
budget together, and we'll do a complete section of it all.
We'll fix the utilities underneath it, and rebuild the street at the same time.
So, if I were a resident watching tonight, I would say, you know, we're just in $13 million
on our streets, where's the evidence that we spent money was well spent?
They are out there.
I call it this map, it's not very easy to see a Pindex A, and a report that you all have, that
second map that's in there.
They're in there, and we can actually go, or maybe it's in there up here.
Which would be a condition zero or one.
The zero's one and two is what would be zero is no pavement, is the way I classed that.
I mean, just looking at this right here, we've got 30 miles of street out there, that's most
of your money that you spend on rebuilding streets.
They're right there, and those ones and two.
I know, as part of the process.
before there were decisions made to try to spread the money among all the
wars to some extent.
And that's one way to prioritize in other ways what you described earlier
and that is to make sure you're at least fixing all of your high traffic
road approach.
And while I think that was 90 percent of what happened last time, there was
some money spent probably on some lower traffic roads that maybe could have been
some of that.
That's Brian's concern.
And the question she's getting reflected that because people would see us working over
an area where it just didn't seem to be that high traffic and why are we spending money
there if we've got problems on a central or whatever.
So I certainly agree with this approach.
And your major roads, they're going to, once they start deteriorating because of the
traffic loads, they'll go quick and some of your residential streets may,
I know they're rough to drive on.
I've drove them.
I've drove every street you guys have.
I know what's out there.
So they're bad, but they don't deteriorate as fast as a D street.
Once it's already got a few spots where it's starting to run and it's just going to
get worse from here, especially with the traffic that's on it.
So that traffic count that's on those just makes those go a lot quicker.
And getting them caught earlier, especially in the maintenance phase,
we'll maybe save you on some of those rebuild costs.
And when you're 13 million ones are going to fix our problem,
but we hope to address most of the major issues at that time.
But we did.
On could you address what we had talked about about the design of some of the
streets and some of those issues where we can stretch our monies a little bit
further.
I think that's very important for this discussion.
We, I had also in geotex read through the existing reports that geotechnical reports
that you guys have had done in the past.
I was more curious on your standard pavement section that you've been using.
It's very conservative for residential street.
I mean, you got 16 inches of base under those streets.
So I had my guys go through and look at those and the traffic counts are a little higher.
Then you would expect for a residential street.
So in turn, that means that your pavement thickness is a little thicker than it should be.
And your base thickness is a little thicker.
And because that total section is so thick, that leads to utility relocates.
And a whole lot of extra dirt that you've got to dig out from underneath those roads
and haul that out.
So our recommendation would be is to set up classes of streets.
Similar to the way that you have, that is.
So your major arterials and your urban collection.
factors, those would be one pavement section.
They would be so many inches of concrete or asphalt and so many inches of base rock
under them and every single one of those are built the same way.
And then you'd step into your secondaries and they would probably be something in between
that and then you would have your locals.
And they're probably going to be something like a six inches of asphalt or concrete over
a six to nine inches base.
But we could cut that base section down a little bit.
Now, that's just going off of the calculations that we've seen in the report.
We've done, like I said earlier, we've done no drilling out here.
I have no idea what's underneath these roads.
But just looking at the traffic counts alone and what they're assuming for the axle loads
seems a little high for residential streets.
And there is some language in there that kind of talks about what my guys were able to find.
John, I used the term over in Geneva and are you saying that perhaps there were a little
over in Geneva for what you would normally see or what you would recommend.
Well, we would see on a residential, yes.
So I'm not saying that D Street may not have 16 inches of base rock under it.
But I'm talking just your standard running the mill residential streets that's got a hundred
guards a day on it.
They probably don't need that much.
The concept in perspective for me is that at a 16 inch base is equivalent to an airport runway.
It's what you're designing to.
In some areas of telling you may need that.
I'm not saying you wouldn't, but if we could do have the same result with six inches of base.
Especially when you look at traffic patterns and things such as that, then obviously we can do a lot more
pavement to that standard.
But again, we do not want to waste money.
We want to make sure once the project is done, it's done properly.
So I think that's the critical thing that we've been trying to look at is, we have to hit
the streets first that we absolutely have to have done.
Keep everything in mind but also have a unified standard that anybody that walks in off the street
can understand what standard we're applying to those street projects that we're working on.
And I think that's the huge value of this.
I think that's important because it sets the expectation.
And this budget has what we assume would be a standard pavement thickness.
It's not your 6 over 16 that you're using on some of your streets today.
So trying to be as conservative as I could on numbers, that realistic at the same time so that
you guys have a fair number to look at and gives you a better idea of what you need to spend.
When I could also add what we were talking about, some of the streets with the testing,
I might be able to do a significant amount of streets by again, slowly sales or chip and sales.
I'll let we did this year with micro-surfacing.
We identified a number of streets that we have that.
But with a micro-surfacing project, like the one that we just did, can probably extend the
lifetime of the number of streets.
I think we're talking about second and third-street northeast, the only main street in the
college, for example, those are some that, with that type of work, probably preserve those
streets for a number of years.
Yeah, that 20 percent that needs maintenance today, that they fall in that category, of just
a simple micro-surfacing, even a crack ceiling program on some of your concrete streets you've
got.
They're still holding up great.
There's a few broken panels here and there, when we get those panels out, get them
replaced.
But start doing a crack ceiling program on them, get those joints sealed up, keep that water
out of them, and you'll be able to keep them for a long time.
Some of them are starting to scale a little bit on top, I know Mike Edwards has talked about
even doing micro-surfacing on them, and they didn't do too bad, they've actually held up very well
because we've pressed with those, so, but that 20 percent that's what falls in those simpler
fixes, and we can extend the life of those streets.
I mean, as you move forward and streets are repaired, don't your traffic count kind of starts
swaying because you're going to show how it's going to start finding the street that's been
done.
I'm going to kick over on that street, and you know, so how do you, that will happen?
You had a road over in the Northwest section that got rebuilt, and the detour road that
they shoved everybody on, it started running, and it's got a section, and it's it's heaved,
and it's because we changed traffic patterns during construction, and that's going to happen.
Hopefully, we can keep up with them, and if it's just a maintenance thing, try and get in there
right afterwards and get them buttoned up, or work with them together, maybe you do rebuild
on the street, and then as soon as you're done with that, you go in afterwards, and you start
doing those adjacent roads that you did on your detours, so that we don't have another incident
where you fixed one ruin road, and you created another.
About three of the things I wanted to just kind of point out of what we're trying to do here.
Number one is we knew when this got started, there's going to be sticker shock, and we knew
that there's just not going to be enough money, but that's not unusual for my Emma.
I think just about every city in America, you can look at something like this, and we'll probably
have the same results.
That my Emma's our responsibility, and that's what we're trying to deal with here.
The second thing is that we're wanting to make sure not only with our rebuild and what we go
out to bid on, but also with what we're doing on maintenance, that's why Richard's here tonight,
too, is just to make sure that we have our maintenance plan kind of highlighting what we're trying
to do with our construction.
That's why crack ceiling is so important, really.
We've got a crack ceiling machine we haven't used in a years.
get it used. You're going to get out and use it. That's why things like the
the Durapatcher that we acquired last year has been doing so well for us. That
you know, fixing the potholes properly and properly the first time. So we keep
pushing at this and I think we can start making some very good progress. I
think we've already made good progress. But it's just, you know, what when you
hear both on a national and statewide basis, the issues about infrastructure
comes down to us as well. And we're probably going to have exactly the same
thicker shock in a month when we talk about our water and our sewer system as
well. So we can only do so much at a time. But again, you know, the old saying
about how you even elephant, that's one bite at a time. We've at least have a
good way of knowing which bites to take and let the public know which bites
we're going to be taking first. The other questions? What do you go from here? Well, where
we go from here is we'll probably start taking a look at this and what the
recommendations were. Bring back to you, obviously, because we want to make sure
for you and also for the public. Everybody understands what our real projects
gonna be. My goal would be that we have them designed and ready to go and out to
bid during the winter. So that we can actually do our bidding. And when spring
rolls around, we can get some of these projects going right away. I've talked
also about one of my concerns is we have a tendency to let bids in April, May and
June. And that means that the projects actually don't get finished until this
time of the year. And now we're having this heat wave in October, but usually by October
you can't do too much work. So ideally, I'd like to be able to have some of these
projects ready to go by say next April and May. I mean, when I say ready to go, ready
to have the equipment and people out there. So I think the next step is going to be
making sure that we have our utility infrastructure taken care of. And that's going to be
the important next month. And then start getting our game plan that we'll be bringing back to
you. Your game plan includes, I'm hoping, what Doug asked, then you come in and we determine
a street, then we do a horse sample and to see whether we need to look at it is going to actually
take place. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. We're going to go look at a street before we do any
design work and see, we'll look at some traffic counts around here and see what we can come
up with. And then actually do some geotech testing. One of our discussions we already have an
engineering design on a de-street. But again, it's to the 16-inch standard. And we want
and that's what we asked for. So it's not like somebody's doing something wrong. We asked for
a 16-inch standard. That's what they gave us. But again, that's one that we'd like to
do the course samples to see. Could that be done with the six inch or does it really need a 16-inch?
So if we go through that process, that's what we'll be able to bring back to you.
to say these streets to this design standard.
So along those lines, I'm getting a little ahead of the game maybe, but the last major
bond issue we had for roads, it was considerable controversy around the specs, which
their roads were designed, whether they were overstepped, as you described some were, and then
whether the contractor met those specs, how are we going to make sure we don't have
those sorts of controversies ever again.
Actually in our contract is to help the city develop standard specifications so that when
you have a developer come in and wants to build something, they can come get specs and
you already have light out how you build your streets and every streets built the same.
And of course, I'd want to sit down with Dean and Alicia and you all, and make sure that
everybody agrees with what we're coming up with, but they're all the same then.
And I'm in this particular case, I'm not referring to a developer all the hopefully we'll have that
concern down the road.
But whoever we put this stuff out to be at, who are my contractors, that they have, not because they
got lines, but specifications, they know they can rely on their requirements to meet and they're
expected to meet, and then we hold them to those standards, and then we don't have that,
you know, again, the controversies, but we had last time, all right.
I, my government hope is that by doing this, we will avoid those controversies, this is the
way to do this, is to have these plans in place, have a firm that can help us through this, and
be very transparent about what we're going to be doing next.
So I've had that very much in mind when this process got started, and I've been very happy
with the result here.
There's a lot of work to be done, there's no way of Sandra Buds, but this is almost like
a comprehensive plan, at least it gives us a good guide and says to what we need to be doing
in the community.
Okay.
One of the question, Mary, I noticed on the map, of course, there's a lot of red, a lot of yellow.
Yes.
I see what you guys are talking about, with this curtain, but at what point, how far along
it does a paint before it turns yellow, and before it turns red?
I mean, I don't see red and yellow getting fixed to the next, you know, all of them being done
in the next 15 years.
Right.
And then, honestly, they're gone.
You're not doing late, it's on them, and so you just regard that, how long until my paint
start turning yellow, and then they're all going to be different, and it just depends on, there's
all those factors out there for it.
What's the traffic, count on them, what's the base underneath it, what's the pavement made
of, and then what's the drainage like in the area?
I noticed a lot of the streets that are starting to rut, and they have those base failures,
they have drainage issues associated with them.
So those are some of the other costs that we're going to need to start.
looking at with these rebuilds and you know my daughter just moved into the country and honestly
her dirt road's not bad and I mean there's a lot better than some of the roads we have and I
didn't know if maybe we could go in there and take some of those tops off and use that I'm not I don't
build roads for a little bit some of those would be mutually improved just by removing the
asphalt it's right you know juggles I don't know if that's uh I know the city's done that in a few
places already where they've they've read it out and it's a long time a year to put asphalt down
so they'll just rock them back and leave them like that counties do it all the time around home it's
not uncommon de-street's been like that for two three weeks now over your road patch about a week
week and a half yeah so I mean it's not boring but you've got that basin there and you've got that
trip traffic on that pack and that in for you sure and then whenever you come back in with your
patch over the top of it hopefully it's pretty solid underneath it so our assumption is that our
citizens want to make sure that whatever street they're driving on that their cars not being knocked
out of alignment and they're not losing the fillings out of their teeth well that is the that's the key
concern right now is to give everybody a smooth ride and there all sorts of ways to give them that smooth
ride what would you recommend I can thank you a couple of hours right now that are
hoard what would you recommend for our alleys that are in that condo we talked about those a little bit
and like I said I had hard surface in there on the alleys but I don't think your alleys are being used
the way they may have been used before you move your trash surface to the streets so
maybe they're not that bad as staying as gravel but put them on a maintenance schedule and have a budget
set aside to where you keep going in and putting rock back in those and maybe they won't get in
as bad of shape those are a lot of cost savings there by not paving your alleys and if they're not being
used the way that an alley would be used if nobody's driving on them the only reason they're there is for
utility access then maybe they just go back and improve completely and you grasp them
pinnicks e these are not representation of my image no they're not that was a job those were built
for joplin I noticed I had the guide before I started I tried to put a few pictures of your
guys as streets in the reports there are my house I have the video so if you guys want to look at those I'll
send them to yeah I can make those available we've got them there's no real good method
for them because their GPS with my program but yeah if you guys want to sit there and watch me drive around
my Emma
the few times myself. We all have. That's similar to what we did. We didn't buy the GoPro but
we went the little cheaper route and it worked well. I mean it's not crystal clear. It's not
like me standing there looking at it but for a guy to go back in the office and three weeks later
sitting there and what if that street looks like it's an excellent record to have and I will be
given it to Lisa when I'm done and that way they've got it so. Other questions? So the plan
being is what's the next step? Next step is what number one is utilities which will be in a month
but in between this is when Sean, Lisa, our staff, Tyler will be involved very much with utilities.
We'll start working on the basic recommendations that you just heard here. We'll be looking at
these trees. We'll be looking at central trying to see if we can get that taken care of.
And then also a pretty good idea about a handle on what we're going to be doing on our maintenance program as
well. What we'll be doing with our street crews. So at then bringing back those plans to you
when building season comes but are actually well before probably these will be winter projects.
Any opportunities to partner with the county? There are two things number one absolutely and the
county has always been rolling to work with us. I think the Tyler told me several years ago that the
county had indicated that they would be more than willing to work with us on the truck route. So I think we need to
outreach to that. The second thing is that by having a plan like this, a grand gateways told us that
if we can give them our plan, if there are going to be grant monies out there, they can kind of
tie grant monies into some of our projects as well. That's one of the, I mean, we're kind of reconnecting with
grand gateways because they've always said we've always been there but we've never really known what your plans are,
what your needs are and if we know what your needs are then we can try to, if we come across money we can find it for you.
And there are a number of projects that the working on that are basically transportation projects that
relate to economic development. That might tie into the truck route very well because that's a commercial route
in town strongly. So by having, I've always said several times the staff, I've always felt like on the
street programs we've been flying blind and now we're not and that's why I'm happy we're doing this and that
we do have this comprehensive plan we can start, you know, looking at what we've got and baking some
corrections. Yeah, a lot of strong encourage you once we get our priority set to sit down with the county
commissioners because they, and the recent past have been really worked well with us on some very
projects and I think at least one brilliant road project and another way.
willing to help.
So, we've been trying to do that resource.
What about public input?
Not that I'm saying, I mean, we're going to make all this available.
It forms me to side, you know, it's on the web now.
Okay.
And by the way, when we did this program, we did have a public input.
We had an open session here, a website.
I think the long lines of what we were hearing for most of the comments, other than just people
hating the streets, is doing more areas.
Most of those streets, there was not a lot of input at the public comment, but the online survey that we posted, it did pretty well.
And most of those were major routes that were picked.
That was one of the stipulations of the question is, besides your street, which one?
Because everybody's going to pick the one at the end of their driveway.
I don't blame them.
But I asked them to think outside of that bubble.
And we got some pretty good feedback, and most of them were major routes.
So we start rolling out the plans through this.
We'll have it out there publicly and ask for input.
You've got other questions?
Okay.
Well, take the first bottle of the alcohol.
There you go.
Thank you.
Okay.
I have a number nine.
Resolution of moving community financial support and a fee waiver to major with a spec building at 36.09.207.
But don't with the used in progress and industrial part.
I hate to start a presentation with an apology, but I think I owe you one.
When we started working with maids on the spec building was being built in progress.
We had always assumed that what we've done for things like Route 66,
Landing, the school projects that would be waiting are building inspection fees,
our connection fees is part of an incentive program for those of you that don't know or are listening.
A spec building is a spec related building.
We're building a 50,000 square foot building in progress.
We hope that somebody is going to be taking that building and creating jobs here in Miami.
That's economic development very, very much.
We had originally talked about the utility extensions to it,
and that they basically cross the construction, which is constructing the building,
recommended, don't do the utility connections at this point,
because whoever buys it might want it in a different location than we would install it.
Because the building is basically going to be a shell.
And that way we can help whoever goes into there and creates jobs.
So we really held off on that and held off on bringing something to you a resolution,
waving the fees.
And then when working with Christie last week, we realized that we are doing inspections out there.
And waving fees doesn't mean we're waving inspections.
We're still doing inspections.
But the question came up, well, do we charge or not?
And I realized they hadn't brought it.
to you, resolution, waiting the inspection fees. So this resolution that we have right now is
waiting the inspection fees and then also waiting the utility connection fees. And again, it's
very similar to what we've approved for Reed 66 landing and we recommend doing it from an economic
development point of view. Will that building have all city utilities? Yes, it's completed. The only
thing that we will anticipate that it depends on who goes into it. They may need natural gas. It
just depends on who takes it. And it will be up to them then if they go with natural gas,
what we're talking about. Our electric argue to our water and our sewer, yes.
Yeah, a question about, come out. We have a lot of curious, you know, what's actually talking about?
Chrissy, do you have an idea about what the fees would be? We're all on the ballpark idea.
Well, you know, not specifically each inspection is $50 plus the $4.00 they feed that goes along with it.
So just depends on how many inspections are needed that the spec building right now is just,
it's just a shell with the footing that's been poured. It's then have a more in it. It doesn't have
any utilities oriented or any more of that. So the only inspections that have been done today
are about our footing inspections. So really, we're probably talking about a minimal cost here. I probably
$1,000 or less at this point. Yeah, yeah. And then this perspective is, it looks forward,
oh, yes, yes, it's looking forward. They kind of like the school ball and
the fees and things that we made, we estimated around $9,000. And that was the work that was
the school ball. So that might kind of give you an idea project. I'm not going to put it in.
I'm not going to put it in. Yeah, I'll second. Roll, roll, please. Tonson?
Right. Weston? Aye. Four-ster? Aye. Shult. Aye. I'm here as proposed charter changes. I know we had a pretty good
discussion at our last work session, which was just last week. And then we asked Ben to
think, clarify a couple of points. And so Ben, I'm just going to turn it over to you, I guess.
To talk about those, specifically, one first. And then we'll talk about two and three.
After that. Okay. So you haven't printed you the seventh draft of the proposed charter in
counting. The couple is on this, is it does not require $1.5 million budget. So
$460 million. Yeah. My computer said that this time, though,
or 116 changes that we made.
And one of the major things were with regards
to the succession of the mayor,
and then some changes with regards
to the election process for removal of a city council member.
The others were, again, reading through it again,
both Christian, I found some various places
where we could combine things, for instance,
not all of our provisions on the qualifications
of being a city council member,
we're in Article 2.
We found some in Article, I think it was Article 6.
So we moved them all to be in the same place.
We took out the language about a elected official
and made it clear we're talking about city council members.
So a lot of those changes were not substantive changes,
but things that helped clarify exactly what we're doing.
The major, like I say, the major changes were outlining
a procedure for successor, succession of the mayor.
So what about mayor, pro-tam?
Which relates to the mayor, pro-tam, right?
You'll see on page four in qualification to see council members,
it looks like there's a whole lot of changes there,
but basically what we've done is taken provisions there.
That I'd failed to gather all together in the previous drafts
and put them all together hopefully,
we've got them all together at this point in that section.
So with that, I think it's mostly a matter of view,
reviewing these and see if there are any other questions
or changes that you would like to have.
Then we updated the language in some places and...
What the city treasure in there, in some place?
Yeah, the city treasure clarified that that is an appointment by you by the council.
On page 12, on the election process.
For the removal, I actually incorporated the state statutes on how that is to be done.
Is that the one panel's successor of any officer or removed?
It's actually right above that.
And we did remove the provision that the council member cannot be removed in the first six months of office.
So, to hand us item two there, is that doable setting of the day-to-speccial election?
I guess.
Okay, so we're just saying, within closing in the filing period.
But we're not putting an end-do card on ourselves.
And we just put it within 30 days.
Everything done within 30 days.
So you thought that through?
Well, I plagiarized.
Okay.
This is what the state law applied.
So, then that's what state law provides and certainly shouldn't create any issues for the county election.
Correct.
Okay.
They should be used today.
Actually, to be a little more correct,
they in the state statute had a minimum time frame, but no maximum time frame.
And so I took their minimum time frame and put in a maximum time frame.
For instance, in one, it's not less than 10 days, no more than 20 days for the filing period.
And did the same sort of thing in section two, the election,
is not less than 45 days, no more than 60 days.
I guess I'm missing this somewhere, I'm skipping over.
The vacancy on the council.
Where's that?
I'm missing that somewhere.
Okay.
I'm just skipping over and out just for a second.
the top of the page, section three, or three, section three, three, and we get this in a finalized form, I'll actually put page number on the page nine.
Okay. Now, what you have in the red line copy is the changes that have been made since the last time brought that.
Right.
Can we talk about this one previously, so that one's been out loud?
Okay.
So in section on page 11, section six, section seven, seven, seven, seven, eight, may have
have his or her name printed upon the on part of the general disposal.
That's probably for any one office to be filled at the election.
So we've had situations that can't ask for someone was a sitting council member and ran for mayor.
But there's no, there's seek was not at that time that they're not precluded from doing that by that language.
Right.
But that's aimed at what this is targeting is you can't run for city council seat.
And the mayor had the same time.
Currently, when currently they're staggered.
So unless you have the situation like Vicki, for example.
Right.
In that situation, theory.
Yeah.
That conflict that she has to run again next time.
Because we're appointment.
Okay.
So I would ask everyone to, since there are, even though most of the changes aren't
there are quite a kind of grant there.
I'd ask everyone to take the time to look through.
Very deliberately read through and I think you're comfortable with everything.
And let me know.
There are no changes in the next meeting.
The program.
So.
Black coffee.
You don't know.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I was one.
My question.
Ben, do you have any concern for what we've talked about?
We might be proposing.
No.
My only concerns for the, the relating to the.
other two propositions, which I made no changes to those, because from the last conversation,
I didn't get there as a desire to have changes to those.
But again, I think that it's a very wise decision to do it as three separate propositions
or the citizens vote on this and then let them express their opinions on the other, whatever
other options you want to present.
Yeah, I mean, my preference is just to table those for right now, just think about them a little bit more.
I'd like to have the information been brought this last time, but the continued to push forward on this primary one.
I mean, that's our kind of the one goal.
The other two can be dealt with administratively if we so choose and make two to do that.
It's important in the future if we don't have been formal propositions.
Any other conversation on this particular agenda item?
When is our goal to wrap this up, Mayor?
You have them.
Then I know we talked a little bit about the calendar last time.
We feel like we're still in good shape, but we really need to, when do we need to have the ballot language to
think it was in January and if it stays with the general election, it is in January when you do
the resolution and the propositions and we get it to them and then the filing for officers and things like that
is in February, but I think once you do the proposition and the resolution you're good on your charter.
Well, I have three more meetings.
Well, counting our work sessions, I guess we have five meetings between now and then.
Let's just, for the second conversation, I should say this is the final document that we're going to ask the voters to approve.
Then we would need to see the ballot language.
Do you have some prepared?
I haven't even started on that, till April.
Would you...
Pretty much figure out what this is, but yeah, you start working on that then because
regardless of what file of form this take was maybe some minor changes, your ballot language is
probably going to be a third of consistent. So I've given that we've got roughly 60 days. We'll just start
working on the ballot language for the prop one.
And maybe we'll hopefully have a draft of that by our next meeting.
We can do that.
Thank you.
Nothing else on that item?
We are going to move to item election.
Which is new business and new business?
Well, there's health on community announcement and announcements. I don't know how to do part to our city manager. I can't
Oh, I got to say is tomorrow night at any else basketball season is a point
Every year when they play their I think it's coffee filled everybody in stands gets handed or roll a tool
And there will be a technical file and when that technical file takes place. That's when everybody heves the rolls a tool
It's an experience you need to go
I think there's a video on YouTube
Five thirty drills tomorrow
It's all
Sorry, I'm more exciting than that
Yeah
The
I really don't have anything. We expect you to bring something
Yeah, I thought she's going to say it's on bottom of the show
Well, we're having lunch in tomorrow with
Several people you've on and Miss Gheeley and we're going to start planning the opening for it
Wish is going to be part of that we're all working right now on a field of punchless items
I think the building is in very good shape. I think there's some issues with the pavement that we're trying to work out with a construction company
But I think everybody has been very happy with the way it's turned out. I believe we've got
Is all the furniture in it?
In it we do have the signs
The dedication signs
We're waiting on some final things that do need to be cleared up with the building before it gets turned over
And then the animal pins have been all installed
I think there's even been some pictures put on Facebook of them being what they were installed
And we basically are doing what we're going to do with the stuff for the inside
There you go. Anna Cruz has also done some work around the area to make sure that the
The drainage is proper to don't have drainage issues as well
So after tomorrow we'll know when the first dog we're going to kind of plan it all
Yes, and also I think one of the things we've talked about is not just the dogs taking up residence
But with a new facility like those who'd like to have new programs
I mean now we have room for being able to host to stay in New York
Now we have room to be able to really put these dogs out for a dog and a whole lot better than we ever had before
The dogs crews are working on an area that will be a green area there
The dogs can actually be during the day instead of being in the cages all the time
So we're hoping that it's not just going to be a place where we're warehousing dogs but it's a place where we find them there for
Ever homes a little bit better than we have in the past
The current facility will still be in place because we're going to always need a place for storage
to need a place every now and then when an animal has to be in quarantine, but such a night and
day's difference between the facility we have now.
I think it's not just for the animals, but I think for the citizens that will go in and try
to find a rescue dog, it's going to put those dogs on display a lot better than we have right
now.
So, where are you going to find range based?
There's actually an area right now that's just slightly too, if you're looking out the front
door just slightly to the left, there's an area that we're going to be redoing some
fencing and putting in some saw from the park's areas, and that will be the green space.
It really works out very well.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
What do we look forward to that?
Item 14 is Executive Session for Sir, 25OS 3072 for discussing negotiations concerning employee
representatives and employee groups to with the FOP and the IAFF.
Do we have a motion you go into Executive Session for the reasons listed on agenda item
14?
I'll take a motion.
Yeah, second.
Second.
roll call please.
Or foraster?
Aye.
Johnson?
Western?
Aye.
Judgment on HFU-S, John Eulish for the Puppet.
I heard very, very, very switch.
That's what he really makes me hate a moment for that.
Okay.
That's just like a game probably.
There's a lot of work.
He didn't even talk me in the ground about it.
Very switcher says.
The rest of it.
Why is it?
Why?
I don't buy anything.
The HFU-S.
That's the same thing.
That is.
I mean, that is in what I think.
He makes a sign.
You're the ones when you're watching TV and I'll send that poor puppy that's just sitting there
in that cage.
Yeah.
Well, okay.
Usually.
But if you buy him what they actually spend.
He's being perched day.
Percentage wise on the money that they make.
You wouldn't say that.
You just need about to.
I don't know.
Okay.
We have most of the job.
I don't know.
Second.
Rope call.
Good question.
First.
Second.
Shelter.
Hi.
Hey, Brian.
That takes back very easy.
I don't know.
I'm sorry.